It Started as a Concert. It Became a Celebration.
The Last Waltz is a documentary, music film directed by Martin Scorsese.
Martin Scorsese's documentary intertwines footage from The Band's incredible farewell tour with probing backstage interviews
and featured performances by Eric Clapton, Bob Dylan, Joni Mitchell, Van Morrison, and other rock legends.
Self, played by Robbie Robertson.
Self, played by Rick Danko.
Self, played by Levon Helm.
Self, played by Richard Manuel.
Self, played by Garth Hudson.
Self, played by Eric Clapton.
The Last Waltz was a concert by the Canadian-American rock group the Band, held on American
Thanksgiving Day, November 25, 1976, at Winterland Ballroom in San Francisco.
The Last Waltz was advertised as the Band's "farewell concert appearance", and the concert had the Band joined by more than a dozen special guests, including
their previous employers Ronnie Hawkins and Bob Dylan, as well as Paul Butterfield, Bobby Charles, Eric Clapton, Neil Diamond, Emmylou Harris, Dr.
John, Joni Mitchell, Van Morrison, the Staple Singers, Ringo
Starr, Muddy Waters, Ronnie Wood, and Neil Young.
The musical director for the concert was the Band's
original record producer, John Simon.
The concert was produced and managed by Bill Graham and was filmed by director Martin
Scorsese, who made it into a documentary of the same title, released in 1978.
Jonathan Taplin, who was the Band's tour manager from 1969 to 1972 and later produced Scorsese's film Mean Streets, suggested that
Scorsese would be the ideal director for the project, and Rock Brynner introduced Robbie Robertson to Scorsese.
Taplin served as executive producer.
The film features concert performances, intermittent song renditions shot on a
studio soundstage, and interviews by Scorsese with members of the Band.
The soundtrack and DVD were later released.
The Last Waltz is hailed as one of the greatest
documentary concert films ever made.
In 2019, the film was selected by the Library of Congress for preservation in the United States
National Film Registry for being "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant".